NYSUT General Officers Records 6174/017
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- History Project; Disaffiliation; Unification; Staff-Line; Pamphlets (Box 1)
  - NYSTA Board of Directors, 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    New York State Teachers Association Salary Policy 1951-1952; A Statement of the Views and Recommendations of the New York State Teachers Association in Regard to Public Education in the State of New York, August 15, 1958; Code of Ethics: Possible Interpretations, n.d.; Council for Administrative Leadership Policy Statement on Desirable Employment Practices, n.d.; An Account of Legal Progress, by John E. Glenn, NYSTA Legal Counsel, August 1959; NYSTA Report the Board of Directors, November 17, 1961; Toward a More Effective Professional Organization, NYSTA, 1959; NYSTA Commission on Professional Practices, Responsibilities, and Rights, 1962-63, August 1963; Report to NYSTA Board of Directors, "Selection of Members of the New York State Teachers Retirement System to Serve on the Retirement Board," by Kenneth De Kay, August 1, 1967
- Representative Assemblies; Reports; Correspondence (Box 2)
  - NYSTA/NYSUT House of Delegates, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    1972 Delegate Handbook; Special House of Delegates Handbook, June 17, 1972; President's Report: 1972, Thomas Y. Hobart; list of Credential Committee; Concord Hotel reservation blank, 1972; "Teacher Unity, Year One: A Report to Delegates 1974"
  - NYSUT Representative Assembly, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Record of roll call votes as listed in New York Teacher, June 18, 1973; record of proceeding, April 1; election summary April 8, 1978; campaign and election procedures, 1978; ballot, April 9, 1978'; list of NYSUT officers and directors elected at 1978 RA
  - NYSTA/NYSUT Miscellaneous Publications, 1957-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    "The Teacher and the Press," by Jean Walrath, NYSTA, re basic press relations, 1957; NYSTA EEO Newsletter, the Equal Educational Opportunity Newsletter of the New York State Teachers Association, featuring article, "Commission Calls for Equal Funding," January-February 1972; "Organizing for Local Action: A Handbook for Local Association Human Relations and EEO Committees" August 1971; NYSUT Affiliated Local Units, including map of regional services centers, November 1974
  - NY State Institution Educators Association, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Letter to president of Civil Service Commission, with attached proposed salary schedule approved unanimously by Coxsackie Chapter of the New York State Institution Educators Association, noting that institution teachers handle the most difficult students, with no pay incentive for longevity or advanced degrees, also noting lack of response from commission, July 18, 1969; letter from association president to members, noting that proposed salary schedule had been sent to Civil Service Commission, and noting that salaries were lower at every point for institutional teachers than for public school teachers, October 25, 1968, with attached minutes of Board of Directors meeting of 10/19/68, criticizing CSEA for poor representation; letter to president of CSEA, urging support with Civil Service Commission for parity with public school teacher, August 8, 1969; PERB decision in matter of County of Fulton and New York State Nurses Association and Civil Services Employees Association that nurses were a separate unit from other employees, with cover memo from attorneys to NYSTA officers G. Howard Goold and Nathan Kullman, April 7, 1969; program for 13th annual convention of NYS Institution Educators Association, May 20, 1968; NYSTA press release announcing convention, with attached list of participants; minutes of NYSIEA Board meeting of January 13, 1968, provided by NYSTA Executive Secretary G. Howard Goold, with attached Statement Submitted by Francis J. Johnston, president, New York State Institutional Educators Association, at the Public Hearing at the Red Room, State Capitol, December 28, 1967, re large disparity in salaries of teachers at state Departments of Correction, Health, Mental Hygiene, and Social Services with teachers at public schools
  - NYSUT/United Teachers Offices Report, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Printed reports
  - NYSUT New Building, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Photos of building under construction at 159 Wolf Rd., Albany, NY, groundbreaking; postcard showing old headquarters at 152 Washington Ave., Albany; memo to local president from Herb Magidson re tentative decision by Board of Directors to move headquarters from leased offices at 80 Wolf Rd., January 20, 1981
  - Aguilar Decision, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    September 1997. U.S. Department of Education Guidance on the Supreme Court's Decision in Agostini v. Felton and Title I (Part A) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act, July 1997, with cover NYSUT Information Bulletin noting that decision overruled 1985 decision, Aguilar v. Felton, which expressly forbade public school teachers from teaching in religiously affiliated private schools; amicus brief by coalition including American Jewish Congress in favor of Aguilar, with cover letter from American Federation of Teachers, March 19, 1997
  - Albert Shanker, 1978-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Press release, "Statement by Albert Shanker, President, American Federation of Teachers, on Education Week "Quality Counts" 50-state report on education," January 15, 1997; letter to the editor of U.S. News and World Report from Shanker, commenting on article "Why Teachers Don't Teacher," February 26, 1996; copy of article; Statement by Albert Shanker, President, American Federation of Teachers, Submitted to the National Governors' Association in Preparation for the White House Education Summit, September 13, 1989; "Asking the Right Questions," delivered by Albert Shanker, President, American Federation of Teachers, at AFT's QuEST '89, July 21, 1989; biography of Shanker; Statement of Albert Shanker, President, American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO, United Federation of Teachers, Local 2, AFT, before a hearing of the New York State Senate Committee on Education, Hon. James H. Donovan, chair, January 15, 1985; National Press Club speech, "A Call for Professionalism: American Federation of Teachers President Albert Shanker Proposes the Creation of a National Exam for New Teachers," January 29, 1985; Statement of Albert Shanker, President, United Federation of Teachers and American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO, before a Legislative Hearing of the New York State Senate Standing Committee on Education, February 10, 1984; MASC Journal (Massachusetts Association of School Committees, Inc.) conference program, including text of speech by Al Shanker re competency testing, October 17, 1980; "In Defense of the University," by Albert Shanker, April 26, 1978; memorial program, April 9, 1997
  - Albert Shanker Institute, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Corporate meeting agenda, May 24, 1999; budget proposal FY 2000; financial statements with report of independent auditors, June 30, 1998 and 1997; bylaws; handwritten note from Roslyn G. Brown, manager, NYSUT Education and Learning Trust, to Chuck Santelli, inquiring about the institute, August 20, 1999
  - Alfonse D'Amato, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Anti-D'Amato ad; newspaper clippings; confidential survey by Peter D. Hart Research Associates re public opinion of New York State construction bond referendum, September 1997; transcript of remarks by Senator D'Amato in Congressional Record
  - Alliance for Quality Education, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Meeting agenda; list of potential demands; list of members as of October 18, 2000; newspaper clippings and list of media coverage of press conference announcing formation of alliance; printed brochure/fact sheet
  - Bill of Rights for Children, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    August 18, 1995. Text of the Regents Bill of Rights for Children: An Education Charter for the Decade of the Child; earlier drafts; AFT special issue of Action, re Responsibility, Respect, Results: Lessons for Life campaign, August 18, 1995; draft of Student Bill of Rights & Responsibilities, April 12, 1989, with cover letter from the New York Bar Association, February 7, 1990; statement by deputy counsel of the New York State School Boards Association, opposing the Student Bill of Rights, November 29, 1988; related correspondence
  - Child Labor Law, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Memo from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to Board of Directors re new child labor law requiring proof of adequate academic performance for 16- and 17-year-olds who wish to work after 10 p.m. on weekdays, need to help develop guidelines, August 26, 1991, with attached copy of legislation; letter from NYS Department of Labor noting that Gov. Mario Cuomo had declared the Decade of the Child and directed the department to undertake a comprehensive review of child labor laws, with attached notice of hearings to be held around the state, June 1, 1988; memo to Tom Hobart, Chuck Santelli (NYSUT director of Research and Educational Services) and Harry Lampman re representation of Tom Hobart at first meeting Department of Labor Advisory Committee on Child Labor Law Review, June 28, 1988, outline of emerging issues, concern that labor shortage was impetus for "modernizing" child labor laws, lack of other labor representation on advisory committee, with attached 1988 Governor's State of the State initiatives on child labor law review; draft paper, "Children at Work," with cover memo to Chuck Santelli, discussing highlights, noting child labor on the rise, enforcement of child labor laws weak, suggested points to include in paper, December 4, 1990
  - Essential Elements of Reading, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Critique to Toni Cortese of Essential Elements of Reading by University of Oregon College of Education director Edward J. Kame'enui, March 13, 1999; Phonetic Awareness Literacy Screening and cover letter from Cortese to Kame'enui, asking for critique, March 15, 1999; critique to Cortese of Essential Elements of Reading and Early Literacy Profile IV, by Marilyn Jager Adams, visiting scholar, Harvard Graduate School of Education, March 22, 1999; draft texts of Essential Elements of Reading and Early Literacy Profile: An Assessment Provided by the New York State Education [Department]
  - Health Care Forum, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    April 24, 2004. American Federation of Teachers (AFT) bound book, State of the Healthcare Workforce 2003; program for Professional Issues Forum on Health Care, April 24, 2004; Glossary of Terms Commonly Used in Health Care, 2004 edition, by AcademyHealth; related correspondence
  - Teacher Compensation, 1996-2006 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Report by Center for American Progress, "Teacher Pay Reforms: The Political Implications of Recent Research," December 2006; AFT resolution, "Part-Time Faculty Compensation and Benefits," n.d.; commentary by AFT vice president Adam Urbanski, "Merit Pay Won't Work in School," Education Week on the Web, January 15, 1997; untitled article on merit pay, by Al Shanker, May 13, 1997; materials by the Consortium for Policy Research in Education (CPRE) Teacher Compensation Project, September 30, 1998; report by CPRE, "School-Based Performance Award Designs: A Case Study," October 1996; Teacher Magazine article, "Rethinking Teacher Pay," April 1998; materials re Newark Central School District pay-for-performance plan, including evaluation forms, tentative contract agreement, and descriptive cover letter, 1996; letter to Toni Cortese from national board certified teacher at Moscow School District 281, Idaho, asking for recommendations for compensation committee, December 5, 1996
  - Teacher Shortage, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    United Federation of Teacher (UFT) printed brochure, The Teacher Shortage in New York City Schools: A crisis threatens our children's education, c. 2000; press releases, "NYSUT: Projected Exodus of Teachers Worse Than Expected," April 6, 2000, and "Statement by New York State United Teachers on Regents' Proposal to Address the Teachers' Shortage," September 12, 2000; memo to NYSUT vice president Toni Cortese for interview re teacher staffing situation at various districts, August 24, 2000; Wall Street Journal newspaper clipping, articles re large number of teachers with emergency certification; statistical data sheets by New York State Teachers Retirement System re retired members as of 2000-2001
  - Teachers for Tomorrow, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    List of participants (districts); memo to Toni Cortese and Chuck Santelli re grant awards, noting displeasure of Utica Teachers Association over the district's disbursement of funds
  - Competency-Based Teacher Education, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Teacher Education Conference Board (TECB) report, "A Review of New York State Competency-Based Teacher Education Trial Projects," October 21, 1974; memos from State Education Department Division of Teacher Education and Certification re changes in requirements for teachers of children with handicapping conditions, with cover letter to NYSUT field staff from NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, May 6, 1975; remarks by Charles Santelli, "NYSUT Views Competency Based Teacher and Teacher Evaluation," presented at the Eighth Conference on Value Inquiry: Value Reassessment in Education, SUNY Geneseo, April 20, 1974; draft paper, "The Governance of Teacher Education by Consortium," by Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., president, NYSUT, presented to the National Consortium of CBTE Developers January 1974; NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services "Summary of the Advisory Opinion of the Attorney General of Texas Concerning Mandatory Performance-Based Teacher Education Programs," n.d., c. January 1974; Selected Resources on Competency Based Teacher Education, courtesy of the NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services (including NYSUT position statement on Regents mandate on competency-based teacher education); NYSUT position and guidelines adopted by the Board of Directors, condemning certification, objecting to the term "competency-based teacher education," strongly objecting to the exploitation of teachers "under the guise of professionalism," accusing Board of Regents of union busting, January 1974. See also Regents Advisory Board: Teacher Education, Certification and Practice
  - Task Force on Teacher Education and Certification, 1977-2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Outline of testimony by Antonia Cortese as witness in court case Gulino v. State Education Department, with cover letter from NYS Office of the Attorney General and attached legal brief, April 1, 2003; Recommendations of the Commissioner's Task Force on Teacher Education and Certification, April 1, 1977; letter to NYSUT vice president Maria Neira from president emeritus Tom Hobart, discussing conversation with Regent Arnold Gardner re training, teaching as a profession, tenure, and other issues, May 25, 2005
  - Teacher Education, Certification and Practice Board (TECAP), 1961-1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Memo to the Board of Regents re creation of an Advisory Board on Teacher Education, Certification, and Practice, November 15, 1962; organizational bylaws and related documents; memo to Chuck Santelli re proposal for autonomous state education standards board, with comparisons with other states, November 14, 1988; proposed roster of members, 1991-92; Evaluation Report of the New York State Teacher Resource and Computer Training Centers (1993-1994), January 1996; TECAP meeting agendas, 1992-96. See also Regents Advisory Board: Teacher Education, Certification and Practice
  - Regents Advisory Board-Teacher Education Certification and Practice, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Memo to the Board of Regents re creation of an Advisory Board on Teacher Education, Certification, and Practice, November 15, 1962; documents re reading certification, including comparisons of requirements in other states; report, "New Approaches to Teacher Education and Certification," report to the Danforth Foundation of the Five College Project, September 1965 - September 1966; discussion draft, "A Career Path for New Educational Personnel in the New York City Public Schools," by the Women's Talent Corps, June 1967; tentative program for the New York State Work Conference on Auxiliary Personnel in Education. See also Competency-Based Teacher Education 1974- 1975
  - Regents Advisory Board-Teacher Education Certification and Practice, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Minutes (some handwritten) of the Regents Advisory Board on Teacher Education, Certification and Practice; State Education Department report, "A Survey of the Preservice Reading Preparation of First-Year Common Branch Teachers in New York State," August 1970; State Education Department tentative draft report, "Reading Problem Analysis Paper," December 1970; related SED documents and correspondence re competence-based certification; list and addresses of members of the Board of Regents as of September 1970
  - Teachshape Meeting, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    April 22, 2004. Printed materials for professional development service organization Teachscape, including overview of services; handwritten notes; facilitative correspondence
  - Tenure (Historical), 1934-1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Pamphlets by the National Education Association of the United States: "Research Bulletin: A Handbook on Teacher Tenure," September 1936; "Tenure Legislation: How to Get It, How to Keep It," May 1944; "Teacher Tenure," October 1944; "Teachers' Contracts: Principles and Practices," March 1945; "Teacher Tenure: Analysis and Appraisal," October 1947; "Report of the Committee on Tenure and Academic Freedom," 1948; "Teacher Tenure Manual," May 1950; "Trends in Teacher Tenure thru Legislation and Court Decision," 1957; papers: "A Study of the Opinion of City Superintendents in Indiana on Tenure," by Donald DuShane, for NEA Proceedings, 1932; abstract for "Indefinite Teacher Tenure," by C. W. Scott, 1935; "Disadvantages of Long and Permanent Tenure" and "Advantages of Long and Permanent Tenure," referenced to Problems of the Teaching Personnel, Dennis Cook, 1930
  - Wicks Law, 1988-2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Background descriptions of the Wicks law; legislative memorandum from NYSUT, urging approval of change to law, December 19, 1988; memorandum of approval by Gov. Mario Cuomo, December 19, 1988; newspaper clipping
  - Speeches-Tom Hobart, 1978-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Statement to the Board of Regents Hearing on a Proposed Professional Board for Teaching, January 31, 1978; testimony of Hobart to the NYS Legislative Institute on the Real Property Tax Crisis: Full Value Assessment and Financing Our Schools, December 3, 1979; Testimony of Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., President, New York State United Teachers, to the Board of Regents Tentative Proposal on Teaching as a Profession and Teacher Competence, calling the proposal an "explosive document" designed to weaken collective bargaining and due process, asserting that the original recommendations of the 1977 Task Force on Teacher Education and Certification were barely recognizable, April 11, 1980; testimony by Hobart to the Standing Committee on Ways & Means, New York State Legislature, on the Impact of the Reagan Administration Budget on New York State, calling it "disastrous," predicting large property tax increases, April 23, 1981; testimony to the Senate Committee on Higher Education, on Education and the Job Market, noting the difference between education and training, September 24, 1982; testimony to the Assembly of the State of New York on Setting Priorities for New York State Public Education in the Future, October 31, 1983; testimony to U.S. House of Representatives Subcommittee on Elementary, Secondary, and Vocational Education, re inadequate funding under Reagan Administration, tax issues, February 19, 1985; testimony at the NYS Senate Education Committee Hearing on Strengthening Teaching in Elementary and Secondary Schools, January 28, 1986; speech, "Study Challenges Teaching in the Next Decade," re survey by Metropolitan Life, c. 1985; speech, "Education Department Concerned about Sailing Skills; Liberty Loses Out to Australia II," 1984, re loss of America's Cup to foreign competitor for first time in 132 years, concern that event was result of laxity in physical education programs, proposed remediation (probably facetious)
  - Speeches/Testimony-Tom Hobart, 1982-1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Testimony of Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., President, New York State United Teachers, to the Board of Regents at Their Legislative Conference, May 23, 1990; testimony to the Temporary State Commission on the Distribution of State Aid to Local School Districts, September 28, 1988; testimony to the New York State Assembly Standing Committee on Higher Education, June 18, 1987; testimony to the New York State Senate Standing Committee on Education, Standing Committee on Labor, Standing Committee on Commerce, Economic Development & Small Business, on Education and Economic Development: Trained for Success in New York State, March 10, 1987; testimony to the Senate Standing Committee on Civil Service and Pension, Assembly Standing Committee on Governmental Employees, May 14, 1986; testimony to the New York State Senate Education Committee Hearing on Strengthening Teaching in Elementary and Secondary Schools, January 28, 1986; Statement of Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., President, New York State United Teachers, at the U.S. House of Representatives Subcommittee on Elementary, Secondary and Vocational Education, February 19, 1985; Testimony of Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., President, New York State United Teachers, to the Board of Regents on the Regents Legislative Proposals, September 10, 1982; testimony to the Standing Committee on Ways and Means, New York State Legislature on the Impact of the Reagan Administration Budget on New York State, calling it "disastrous," predicting large property tax increases, April 23, 1981
  - Editorial-Tom Hobart, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Editorials by NYSUT president Hobart, apparently for New York Teacher, most not dated
  - Speeches-Chuck Santelli, 1988-1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)